Deeming Sunday the best day for taking Mr. Wemmick’s Walworth sentiments, I devoted the
next ensuing Sunday afternoon to a pilgrimage to the Castle. On arriving before the battlements,
I found the Union Jack flying and the drawbridge up; but undeterred by this show of defiance
and resistance, I rang at the gate, and was admitted in a most pacific manner by the Aged.
“My son, sir,” said the old man, after securing the drawbridge, “rather had it in his mind that
you might happen to drop in, and he left word that he would soon be home from his afternoon’s
walk. He is very regular in his walks, is my son. Very regular in everything, is my son.”
I nodded at the old gentleman as Wemmick himself might have nodded,
and we went in and sat down by the fireside.
“You made acquaintance with my son, sir,” said the old man, in his chirping way,
while he warmed his hands at the blaze, “at his office, I expect?” I nodded. “Hah! I have
heerd that my son is a wonderful hand at his business, sir?” I nodded hard. “Yes;
so they tell me. His business is the Law?” I nodded harder. “Which makes it more surprising
in my son,” said the old man, “for he was not brought up to the Law, but to the Wine-Coopering.”
Curious to know how the old gentleman stood informed concerning the reputation of Mr. Jaggers,
I roared that name at him. He threw me into the greatest confusion by laughing heartily
and replying in a very sprightly manner, “No, to be sure; you’re right.” And to
this hour I have not the faintest notion what he meant, or what joke he thought I had made.
As I could not sit there nodding at him perpetually, without making some other
attempt to interest him, I shouted at inquiry whether his own calling in life had been “the
Wine-Coopering.” By dint of straining that term out of myself several times and tapping the old
gentleman on the chest to associate it with him, I at last succeeded in making my meaning understood.
“No,” said the old gentleman; “the warehousing, the warehousing. First, over yonder;” he appeared
to mean up the chimney, but I believe he intended to refer me to Liverpool; “and then
in the City of London here. However, having an infirmity—for I am hard of hearing, sir—”
I expressed in pantomime the greatest astonishment.
“—Yes, hard of hearing; having that infirmity coming upon me, my son he went into the Law,
and he took charge of me, and he by little and little made out this elegant and
beautiful property. But returning to what you said, you know,” pursued the old man,
again laughing heartily, “what I say is, No to be sure; you’re right.”
I was modestly wondering whether my utmost ingenuity would have enabled me
to say anything that would have amused him half as much as this imaginary pleasantry,
when I was startled by a sudden click in the wall on one side of the chimney,
and the ghostly tumbling open of a little wooden flap with “JOHN” upon it. The old man, following
my eyes, cried with great triumph, “My son’s come home!” and we both went out to the drawbridge.
It was worth any money to see Wemmick waving a salute to me from the other side of the moat,
when we might have shaken hands across it with the greatest ease. The Aged was so delighted
to work the drawbridge, that I made no offer to assist him, but stood quiet until Wemmick
had come across, and had presented me to Miss Skiffins; a lady by whom he was accompanied.
Miss Skiffins was of a wooden appearance, and was, like her escort, in the post-office branch
of the service. She might have been some two or three years younger than Wemmick, and I judged
her to stand possessed of portable property. The cut of her dress from the waist upward,
both before and behind, made her figure very like a boy’s kite; and I might have pronounced her gown
a little too decidedly orange, and her gloves a little too intensely green. But she seemed to be
a good sort of fellow, and showed a high regard for the Aged. I was not long in discovering that
she was a frequent visitor at the Castle; for, on our going in, and my complimenting Wemmick on
his ingenious contrivance for announcing himself to the Aged, he begged me to give my attention
for a moment to the other side of the chimney, and disappeared. Presently another click came,
and another little door tumbled open with “Miss Skiffins” on it; then Miss Skiffins shut up and
John tumbled open; then Miss Skiffins and John both tumbled open together, and finally shut
up together. On Wemmick’s return from working these mechanical appliances, I expressed the
great admiration with which I regarded them, and he said, “Well, you know, they’re both pleasant
and useful to the Aged. And by George, sir, it’s a thing worth mentioning, that of all the people
who come to this gate, the secret of those pulls is only known to the Aged, Miss Skiffins, and me!”
“And Mr. Wemmick made them,” added Miss Skiffins, “with his own hands out of his own head.”
While Miss Skiffins was taking off her bonnet (she retained her green gloves during the evening
as an outward and visible sign that there was company), Wemmick invited me to take a
walk with him round the property, and see how the island looked in wintertime. Thinking that
he did this to give me an opportunity of taking his Walworth sentiments, I seized the opportunity
as soon as we were out of the Castle. Having thought of the matter with care,
I approached my subject as if I had never hinted at it before. I informed Wemmick that I was
anxious in behalf of Herbert Pocket, and I told him how we had first met, and how we had fought.
I glanced at Herbert’s home, and at his character, and at his having no means but
such as he was dependent on his father for; those, uncertain and unpunctual. I
alluded to the advantages I had derived in my first rawness and ignorance from his society,
and I confessed that I feared I had but ill repaid them, and that he might have done better without
me and my expectations. Keeping Miss Havisham in the background at a great distance, I still
hinted at the possibility of my having competed with him in his prospects, and at the certainty
of his possessing a generous soul, and being far above any mean distrusts, retaliations, or
designs. For all these reasons (I told Wemmick), and because he was my young companion and friend,
and I had a great affection for him, I wished my own good fortune to reflect some rays upon him,
and therefore I sought advice from Wemmick’s experience and knowledge of men and affairs, how
I could best try with my resources to help Herbert to some present income,—say of a hundred a year,
to keep him in good hope and heart,—and gradually to buy him on to some small partnership. I begged
Wemmick, in conclusion, to understand that my help must always be rendered without Herbert’s
knowledge or suspicion, and that there was no one else in the world with whom I could advise.
I wound up by laying my hand upon his shoulder, and saying, “I can’t help confiding in you, though
I know it must be troublesome to you; but that is your fault, in having ever brought me here.”
Wemmick was silent for a little while, and then said with a kind of start,
“Well you know, Mr. Pip, I must tell you one thing. This is devilish good of you.”
“Say you’ll help me to be good then,” said I.
“Ecod,” replied Wemmick, shaking his head, “that’s not my trade.”
“Nor is this your trading-place,” said I.
“You are right,” he returned. “You hit the nail on the head. Mr. Pip,
I’ll put on my considering-cap, and I think all you want to do may be done by degrees.
Skiffins (that’s her brother) is an accountant and agent. I’ll look him up and go to work for you.”
“I thank you ten thousand times.”
“On the contrary,” said he, “I thank you, for though we are strictly in our private and personal
capacity, still it may be mentioned that there are Newgate cobwebs about, and it brushes them away.”
After a little further conversation to the same effect, we returned into the Castle where we found
Miss Skiffins preparing tea. The responsible duty of making the toast was delegated to the Aged,
and that excellent old gentleman was so intent upon it that he seemed to me in
some danger of melting his eyes. It was no nominal meal that we were going to make,
but a vigorous reality. The Aged prepared such a hay-stack of buttered toast, that I
could scarcely see him over it as it simmered on an iron stand hooked on to the top-bar;
while Miss Skiffins brewed such a jorum of tea, that the pig in the back premises
became strongly excited, and repeatedly expressed his desire to participate in the entertainment.
The flag had been struck, and the gun had been fired, at the right moment of time,
and I felt as snugly cut off from the rest of Walworth as if the moat were thirty feet wide by
as many deep. Nothing disturbed the tranquillity of the Castle, but the occasional tumbling open of
John and Miss Skiffins: which little doors were a prey to some spasmodic infirmity that made me
sympathetically uncomfortable until I got used to it. I inferred from the methodical nature of Miss
Skiffins’s arrangements that she made tea there every Sunday night; and I rather suspected that a
classic brooch she wore, representing the profile of an undesirable female with a very straight nose
and a very new moon, was a piece of portable property that had been given her by Wemmick.
We ate the whole of the toast, and drank tea in proportion, and it was delightful
to see how warm and greasy we all got after it. The Aged especially, might have passed
for some clean old chief of a savage tribe, just oiled. After a short pause of repose,
Miss Skiffins—in the absence of the little servant who, it seemed, retired to the bosom
of her family on Sunday afternoons—washed up the tea-things, in a trifling lady-like
amateur manner that compromised none of us. Then, she put on her gloves again,
and we drew round the fire, and Wemmick said, “Now, Aged Parent, tip us the paper.”
Wemmick explained to me while the Aged got his spectacles out, that this was according to custom,
and that it gave the old gentleman infinite satisfaction to read the news aloud. “I won’t
offer an apology,” said Wemmick, “for he isn’t capable of many pleasures—are you, Aged P.?”
“All right, John, all right,” returned the old man, seeing himself spoken to.
“Only tip him a nod every now and then when he looks off his paper,” said Wemmick,
“and he’ll be as happy as a king. We are all attention, Aged One.”
“All right, John, all right!” returned the cheerful old man,
so busy and so pleased, that it really was quite charming.
The Aged’s reading reminded me of the classes at Mr. Wopsle’s great-aunt’s, with the pleasanter
peculiarity that it seemed to come through a keyhole. As he wanted the candles close to him,
and as he was always on the verge of putting either his head or the newspaper into them,
he required as much watching as a powder-mill. But Wemmick was equally untiring and gentle in his
vigilance, and the Aged read on, quite unconscious of his many rescues. Whenever he looked at us,
we all expressed the greatest interest and amazement, and nodded until he resumed again.
As Wemmick and Miss Skiffins sat side by side, and as I sat in a shadowy corner,
I observed a slow and gradual elongation of Mr. Wemmick’s mouth, powerfully suggestive of his
slowly and gradually stealing his arm round Miss Skiffins’s waist. In course of time I saw his hand
appear on the other side of Miss Skiffins; but at that moment Miss Skiffins neatly stopped him with
the green glove, unwound his arm again as if it were an article of dress, and with the greatest
deliberation laid it on the table before her. Miss Skiffins’s composure while she did this was one
of the most remarkable sights I have ever seen, and if I could have thought the act consistent
with abstraction of mind, I should have deemed that Miss Skiffins performed it mechanically.
By and by, I noticed Wemmick’s arm beginning to disappear again, and gradually fading out
of view. Shortly afterwards, his mouth began to widen again. After an interval of suspense on
my part that was quite enthralling and almost painful, I saw his hand appear on the other
side of Miss Skiffins. Instantly, Miss Skiffins stopped it with the neatness of a placid boxer,
took off that girdle or cestus as before, and laid it on the table. Taking the table to represent the
path of virtue, I am justified in stating that during the whole time of the Aged’s reading,
Wemmick’s arm was straying from the path of virtue and being recalled to it by Miss Skiffins.
At last, the Aged read himself into a light slumber. This was the time for Wemmick to produce
a little kettle, a tray of glasses, and a black bottle with a porcelain-topped cork, representing
some clerical dignitary of a rubicund and social aspect. With the aid of these appliances we all
had something warm to drink, including the Aged, who was soon awake again. Miss Skiffins mixed,
and I observed that she and Wemmick drank out of one glass. Of course I knew better than to
offer to see Miss Skiffins home, and under the circumstances I thought I had best go first;
which I did, taking a cordial leave of the Aged, and having passed a pleasant evening.
Before a week was out, I received a note from Wemmick, dated Walworth, stating that he hoped he
had made some advance in that matter appertaining to our private and personal capacities, and that
he would be glad if I could come and see him again upon it. So, I went out to Walworth again,
and yet again, and yet again, and I saw him by appointment in the City several times,
but never held any communication with him on the subject in or near Little Britain. The upshot was,
that we found a worthy young merchant or shipping-broker, not long established in business,
who wanted intelligent help, and who wanted capital, and who in due course of time and
receipt would want a partner. Between him and me, secret articles were signed of which Herbert was
the subject, and I paid him half of my five hundred pounds down, and engaged for sundry
other payments: some, to fall due at certain dates out of my income: some, contingent on
my coming into my property. Miss Skiffins’s brother conducted the negotiation. Wemmick
pervaded it throughout, but never appeared in it. The whole business was so cleverly managed,
that Herbert had not the least suspicion of my hand being in it. I never shall
forget the radiant face with which he came home one afternoon, and told me,
as a mighty piece of news, of his having fallen in with one Clarriker (the young merchant’s name),
and of Clarriker’s having shown an extraordinary inclination towards him, and of his belief that
the opening had come at last. Day by day as his hopes grew stronger and his face brighter, he must
have thought me a more and more affectionate friend, for I had the greatest difficulty
in restraining my tears of triumph when I saw him so happy. At length, the thing being done,
and he having that day entered Clarriker’s House, and he having talked to me for a whole evening in
a flush of pleasure and success, I did really cry in good earnest when I went to bed, to think that
my expectations had done some good to somebody. A great event in my life, the turning point of my
life, now opens on my view. But, before I proceed to narrate it, and before I pass on to all the
changes it involved, I must give one chapter to Estella. It is not much to give to the theme that
so long filled my heart. Chapter 38.